<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Ruby | Written by Thorsten Ball]]></title>
  <link href="http://mrnugget.github.com/blog/categories/ruby/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mrnugget.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-01-15T09:09:34+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://mrnugget.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Thorsten Ball]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[mrnugget@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ordered Search Autocompletion With Redis]]></title>
    <link href="http://mrnugget.github.com/blog/2012/06/08/search-autocompletion-with-redis/"/>
    <updated>2012-06-08T16:42:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://mrnugget.github.com/blog/2012/06/08/search-autocompletion-with-redis</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I spent the last weekend building a caching system for <a href="http://anygood.heroku.com" title="Any Good">AnyGood</a>
using <a href="http://www.redis.io" title="Redis">Redis</a> to save API responses for certain
amount of time. Since the next item on my TODO list was autocompletion for my search
form I started googling around looking for solutions involving Redis. I
stumbled upon two great posts examining this particular topic: The <a href="http://antirez.com/post/autocomplete-with-redis.html" title="Autocomplete with Redis">first one</a>
written by Salvatore Sanfilippo is a great explanation on how to use
Redis for autocompletion and goes in great detail when explainin the algorithm.
The <a href="http://patshaughnessy.net/2011/11/29/two-ways-of-using-redis-to-build-a-nosql-autocomplete-search-index" title="Two ways of using Redis to build a NoSQL autocomplete search index">second one</a>
by Pat Shaughnessy is a great help when explaining Sanfilippos algorithm and comparing
it to <a href="https://github.com/seatgeek/soulmate" title="Soulmate">Soulmate</a>, "a tool to
help solve the common problem of developing a fast autocomplete feature. It uses
Redis's sorted sets to build an index of partially completed words and the
corresponding top matching items, and provides a simple sinatra app to query
them."</p>

<p>So I spent a good amount of time studying those articles and reading through the
source code of Soulmate before I decided to write my own solution. Why? Because
it was a rainy sunday afternoon, playing around with Redis is fun and I wanted
to learn more about it. Plus: I wanted multiple phrase matching and
search result ordering. Soulmate did all that and a bit more but just setting
it up wouldn't have the same learning effect. And since I was out to play, I
might as well have fun. So let's see how to this...</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>What it should do</h2>

<p>Let's suppose we want autocompletion for our search form that not only returns a
single value for each proposed item but also comes with some data that we can
present. Also, let's go one step further and say that the search form
should present the items available to the user in an ordered way, e.g. by
popularity.</p>

<p>So when a user types into the search form, we want to to show him all the
possible movies matching his search phrases. That means the first thing we've
got to do is dump the data we want to present into Redis. Like Soulmate, we use
a <a href="http://redis.io/topics/data-types#hashes" title="Redis Hashes">Redis hash</a> here,
where each movie has its own unique key. The key can be anything as long as it's
unique. If you don't have unique IDs for your data, you could use MD5 to
generate some. But let's suppose we do have an unique ID, dumping the data into
Redis is pretty simple:</p>

<p><code>
HSET moviesearch:data 1 "{\"name\":\"Kill Bill\",\"year\":2003}"
HSET moviesearch:data 2 "{\"name\":\"King Kong\",\"year\":2005}"
HSET moviesearch:data 3 "{\"name\":\"Killer Elite\",\"year\":2011}"
HSET moviesearch:data 4 "{\"name\":\"Kill Bill 2\",\"year\":2004}"
HSET moviesearch:data 5 "{\"name\":\"Kilts for Bill\",\"year\":2027}"
HSET moviesearch:data 6 "{\"name\":\"Kids\",\"year\":1995}"
HSET moviesearch:data 7 "{\"name\":\"Kindergarten Cop\",\"year\":1990}"
HSET moviesearch:data 8 "{\"name\":\"The Green Mile\",\"year\":1999}"
HSET moviesearch:data 9 "{\"name\":\"The Dark Knight\",\"year\":2008}"
HSET moviesearch:data 10 "{\"name\":\"The Dark Knight Rises\",\"year\":2012}"
</code></p>

<p><code>HSET</code> is the Redis command to save something into a hash. The key for this
hash is <code>moviesearch:data</code>. The single keys for every movie in this hash are the
unique IDs: <em>1, 2, 3, ...</em>. And the data we're saving are JSON strings, which
represent a pretty convenient way of saving objects to Redis. Also, it's easy enough
in Ruby to convert a Ruby hash to JSON and after retrieving it from Redis back
to a hash:</p>

<p>```ruby
require 'json'</p>

<h1>Before dumping to Redis:</h1>

<p>{name: 'Kill Bill', year: 2003}.to_json</p>

<h1>=> "{\"name\":\"Kill Bill\",\"year\":2003}"</h1>

<h1>After retrieving from Redis:</h1>

<p>JSON.parse("{\"name\":\"Kill Bill\",\"year\":2003}")</p>

<h1>=> {"name"=>"Kill Bill", "year"=>2003}</h1>

<p>```</p>

<p>Oh and btw. I'm using <a href="https://github.com/redis/redis-rb" title="redis-rb">redis-rb</a>
as the Ruby client to connect to Redis, which does not only support Redis
transactions and pipelining, but the best thing about this client is that the
<a href="http://www.redis.io/commands" title="Redis commands">Redis commands</a> have the same
name and take the same arguments (well, most of the time), which is especially
great when getting to know Redis and looking up commands in the documentation.
So now we've got the movies in Redis, how do we find them again?</p>

<h2>Prefixes everywhere!</h2>

<p>People are most likely trying to search for a movie by starting to type its name
into the input field. And we want to show them the matching movies before
they're even finished typing the whole name, right? That's why we're talking
about autocompletion here. That means we need an association between word
prefixes and the movies. If someone were to type in <em>The Dar</em> we want to
show <em>The Dark Knight</em> and <em>The Dark Knight Rises</em> as possible search terms.
Long story short: we need to get the prefixes of every movie we just dumped in our
<code>moviesearch:data</code> hash. For that I'm using a simple method, which is heavily based
on the one Sanfilippo uses in his example script:</p>

<p>```ruby
def prefixes_for(string)
  prefixes = []
  words    = string.downcase.split(' ')</p>

<p>  words.each do |word|
  (1..word.length).each {|i| prefixes &lt;&lt; word[0...i] unless i == 1}
  end</p>

<p>  prefixes
end
```</p>

<p>The movie with the name <em>The Dark Knight</em> will result in the following prefixes:
```ruby
prefixes_for('The Dark Knight')</p>

<h1>=> ["th", "the", "da", "dar", "dark", "kn", "kni", "knig", "knigh", "knight"]</h1>

<p>```</p>

<p>And <em>The Dark Knight Rises</em> will result in the following prefixes:
```ruby
prefixes_for('The Dark Knight Rises')</p>

<h1>=> ["th", "the", "da", "dar", "dark", "kn", "kni", "knig", "knigh", "knight", "ri", "ris", "rise", "rises"]</h1>

<p>```</p>

<p>We need to generate those prefixes for every movie we want to use in our search
autocompletion and so I use a minimum prefix length of two characters here,
because using one character prefixes is a lot of overhead for search completion
where most people are going to type in more than one character.</p>

<p>(Of course it's entirely possible to not only use prefixes, but use every range
of characters from any position in the word. Instead of using <em>fi, fis, fish</em>
for <em>Fish</em>, we could use <em>fi, fis, fish, is, ish, sh</em>. But people are more
likely to type the beginning of a word, I guess.)</p>

<h2>Save those prefixes to sorted sets!</h2>

<p>Redis uses <a href="http://redis.io/topics/data-types#sorted-sets" title="Sorted
Sets">sorted sets</a> as a list of unique strings that can be ranked by a score. For now, we
will ignore the score and just use this as a set where every entry is unique and
trying to add one with the same name won't result in a new entry. So let's
create a sorted set for every prefix. This set will include the key of the
movies in which the prefix occurs and the pattern for those keys is the one
Soulmate uses: <code>moviesearch:index:$PREFIX</code>.</p>

<p>In order to associate the movie <em>The Dark Knight</em> with its prefixes we need
to do the following for every prefix:</p>

<p><code>
ZADD moviesearch:index:dar 0 9
</code></p>

<p>As you might have guessed, the prefix here is <em>dar</em>. The next number in this
command is the score the member of this sorted set will have, but as I said,
ignore this for now and keep in mind that the <code>9</code> is the key of our <code>moviesearch:data</code>
hash pointing to the <em>The Dark Knight</em>. So we need to associate all prefixes of
every moviename with its key in the <code>moviesearch:data</code> hash. Written in Ruby a
method doing exactly that would look like this:</p>

<p>```ruby
def add_movie(movie_name, data_hash_key)
  prefixes = prefixes_for(movie_name)</p>

<p>  prefixes.each do |prefix|</p>

<pre><code>REDIS.zadd("moviesearch:index:#{prefix}", 0, data_hash_key)
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>That's pretty simple, isn't it? The method takes two arguments: the name of the
movie and the key of the <code>moviesearch:data</code> hash pointing to its data. After
using that method for all the movies we added to our data hash, we have a lot of
sorted sets with its members being the keys for our data hash. That means, after
adding <em>The Dark Knight</em> and <em>The Dark Knight Rises</em> the
<code>moviesearch:index:dark</code> set has two members: <code>9</code> and <code>10</code>. So, what does that
give us?</p>

<p>Let's imagine a user is visiting our website and typing <em>dar</em> into the input
field of the search form.</p>

<p>We now get all the entries in <code>moviesearch:index:dar</code>, which are the keys of our
moviesearch:data hash. The sorted set with the key <code>moviesearch:index:dar</code>
contains <code>9</code> and <code>10</code> as members. With those numbers we can now just fetch all
the hash entries with these as key and present them to the user. But
let's see how that works.</p>

<h2>Matching more than one word using Redis' <code>ZINTERSTORE</code></h2>

<p>If we want to get all the entries for <code>moviesearch:index:ki</code> we use the ZRANGE
command provided by Redis:</p>

<p><code>
ZRANGE moviesearch:index:dar 0 -1
</code></p>

<p>Starting from the first element (<code>0</code> since Redis starts indexing with 0) and going
to the last (<code>-1</code>) we get the hash keys for movies whose names contain the prefix 'dar':</p>

<p><code>bash
$ redis-cli ZRANGE moviesearch:index:dar 0 -1
1) "9"
2) "10"
</code></p>

<p>And now, let's fetch all the entries from our <code>moviesearch:data</code> with those
keys:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ redis-cli HMGET moviesearch:data 9 10
1) "{\"name\":\"The Dark Knight Rises\",\"year\":2008}"
2) "{\"name\":\"The Dark Knight\",\"year\":2008}"
</code></p>

<p>Instead of using <code>HGET</code> we use <code>HMGET</code> to fetch multiple hash entries. That's
quite neat! Now we have all the movies containing a word that starts with
'dar'. And we could present those to the user, who is typing and waiting for
suggestions. Let's go one step further though:</p>

<p>Let's suppose a user has typed <em>ki bi</em> into our search form. We now want to
present him <em>Kill Bill</em>, <em>Kill Bill 2</em>, <em>Kilts for Bill</em> as suggestions, but not
<em>Killer Elite</em> and not <em>King Kong</em>. That means we need to find a movie
containing both those prefixes in its name and not only one of them. And this is
exactly where Redis' <a href="http://redis.io/commands/zinterstore" title="Redis ZINTERSTORE command">ZINTERSTORE</a>
comes out to play.</p>

<p><code>ZINTERSTORE</code> creates a new sorted with a given key containing all the members
occuring in the sets passed to it. Let's use it to create a temporary set
containing the hash keys of the movies having 'ki bi' in their names:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ redis-cli ZINTERSTORE moviesearch:index:ki|bi 2 moviesearch:index:ki moviesearch:index:bi
</code></p>

<p>What happens here? <code>ZINTERSTORE</code> looks up which members are in both
<code>moviesearch:index:ki</code> and <code>moviesearch:index:bi</code> and creates a new sorted set
with the key <code>moviesearch:index:ki|bi</code> containing those members. The pattern for
this key is also from Soulmate: dig through the code as there are lots of great
ideas! Now we can use the <code>ZRANGE</code> command again and see which movies contain
those prefixes:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ redis-cli ZRANGE 'moviesearch:index:ki|bi'
1) "1"
2) "4"
3) "5"
</code></p>

<p>And those are exactly the keys pointing to <em>Kill Bill</em>, <em>Kill Bill 2</em> and <em>Kilts
For Bill</em> in the <code>moviesearch:data</code> hash! Great! All we have to do now is use
<code>HMGET</code> to get the data for those keys from the hash and present them to the
user.</p>

<h2>Score &amp; Popularity</h2>

<p>Until now we ignored the score of our sorted sets. But let's say all our users
are looking up <em>Kill Bill</em> by typing in <em>Ki Bi</em> and hitting enter. Let's also
assume there are a lot more users looking up <em>Kill Bill</em> than there are people
interested in <em>Kindergarten Cop</em> (as weird as this assumption may sound, bear
with me here). Remember when we associated the movies with the prefixes? We did
this, using <code>0</code> as the score:</p>

<p><code>
ZADD moviesearch:index:ki 0 1
</code></p>

<p>Now, everytime a person looks up <em>Kill Bill</em> instead of <em>Kindergarten Cop</em> we
can increment the score of the <code>1</code> entry (pointing to <em>Kill Bill</em>) in the
<code>moviesearch:index:ki</code> set (and all the other sets containing <code>1</code>) using
<a href="http://redis.io/commands/zincrby" title="Redis ZINCRBY command">ZINCRBY</a>. <code>ZINCRBY</code>
increments the score of a given member in a given set by a given value. In order
to sort our results by popularity we could increment the score of a given movie
everytime a user looks that movie up. A simple method for doing this would
probably look like this:</p>

<p>```ruby
def incr_score_for(movie_name, data_hash_key)
  prefixes    = prefixes_for(movie_name)</p>

<p>  prefixes.each do |prefix|</p>

<pre><code>REDIS.zincrby(index_key_for(prefix), 1, data_hash_key)
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>We take every prefix occuring in the movie name and increment the score of the
member pointing to the movie's data in the <code>moviesearch:data</code> hash.</p>

<p>Now, before thinking about scores of set members we used <code>ZRANGE</code> to get the
members of a given set. Working with scores now, the next time we try to
match a movie with the given prefixes we'll use
<a href="http://redis.io/commands/zrevrange" title="Redis ZREVRANGE command">ZREVRANGE</a> to
return the matching hash keys ordered by their respective score. The following
should then give us <em>Kill Bill</em> at the top after we incremented the score for
this movie every time a user looks it up.</p>

<p><code>
ZREVRANGE  moviesearch:index:ki 0 -1
</code></p>

<p>Using <code>ZREVRANGE</code>, <code>ZUNIONSTORE</code> and <code>HMGET</code> combined we can write a Ruby method
to look up movies matching the passed prefixes and order them by score:</p>

<p>```ruby
def find_by_prefixes(prefixes)
  intersection_key = index_key_for(prefixes)
  index_keys       = prefixes.map {|prefix| index_key_for(prefix)}</p>

<p>  REDIS.zinterstore(intersection_key, index_keys)
  REDIS.expire(intersection_key, 7200)</p>

<p>  data_hash_keys  = REDIS.zrevrange(intersection_key, 0, -1)
  matching_movies = REDIS.hmget(data_key, *data_hash_keys)</p>

<p>  matching_movies.map {|movie| JSON.parse(movie, symbolize_names: true)}
end
```</p>

<p>This method takes an array of prefixes as argument, creating the index keys for
them, then it creates a temporary sorted set using <code>ZINTERSTORE</code> (<code>EXPIRE</code> tells Redis to delete a
given key after the specified time in seconds) containing the data hash keys
pointing to the movies. After that <code>ZREVRANGE</code> gives us all the members of this
set ordered by their score and finally <code>HMGET</code> is used to get the data for all
the matching keys from the <code>moviesearch:data</code> hash. There are a couple of helper
methods involved, but it should still be pretty clear what happens. If not, look
at the code of the whole <code>MovieMatcher</code> class I use in Anygood <a href="https://gist.github.com/2900740" title="Anygood MovieMatcher class">here</a>.</p>

<p>So everything combined we use Redis hashes to save our data, sorted sets for
every prefix whose members point at our movies in the hash and in order to find
movies containing multiple prefixes we use <code>ZINTERSTORE</code> as a cache to point us
to the movies containing both. And now we've got search autocompletion
presenting ordered results to the user matching multiple phrases!</p>

<p>If you want to dig deeper, please read through the source code of Soulmate and
study those two articles mentioned in the first paragraph. They both do a great
job at explaining what exactly is going on here and why to use sorted sets and
the other data types as we do.</p>

<p>And if you're not <a href="http://www.twitter.com/herrbrocken" title="Follow me!">following me on Twitter</a>
you're missing out!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
